Guide to the Records of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for Gospel Ministry MC.108
New York University Archives
Records of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for Gospel Ministry
1815-1834
New York University Archives
American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry
American Education Society
MC.108
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
The American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry was established in 1815 with the goal of providing financial support to men seeking a theological education. The Records of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for Gospel Ministry is a collection of annual reports of the society from 1815-1834. Adopted in 1815, the organization's constitution was printed in every subsequent report. Each report also contains a yearly summary of organizational activities, and lists of beneficiaries, donors, lifetime members, and annual subscribers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open with restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was transferred from NYU's Washington Square Library to the University Archives sometime prior to August 1990.
Arrangement
The original order of the collection was retained; this collection is in chronological order.
Historical Note
The American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry was founded in 1815, with the intention of increasing the number of ministers within the United States. The organizers felt that there were not enough men being educated as ministers, and that a vast percentage of the population were without religious guidance and instruction. Therefore, the mission of the society was to provide financially for young men who wished to join the ministry, but could not afford such an education. The society was renamed the American Education Society in 1820, and continued to function as a scholarship organization that provided financial support for students in theology programs.
The Reverend Dr. Woods, Reverend Joshua Bates and Mr. John Adams are listed in the first journal as the first leaders of the organizations. A few notable figures from NYU and American history include; Gardiner Spring, William Patton, James Milnor, Frances Scott Key, James M. Matthews, the 1st chancellor of NYU, and Hon. Theodore Frelinghuysen, the 2nd Chancellor of NYU, and later President of Rutgers University.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of annual reports from the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for Gospel Ministry. The first document in this collection is dated 1815, the year of the inaugural annual meeting of directors. The collection document meetings up to 1834, although the society continued to function under various names well into the 20th century.
The American Society for Educating Pious Youth for Gospel Ministry adopted a constitution on August 29th, 1815, which outlined the terms of admission and subsistence within the organization. The constitution was printed in every subsequent report. Each report also contains a yearly summary of organizational activities, and lists of beneficiaries, donors, lifetime members (people who donated $100 at any given time were considered automatic lifetime members), and annual subscribers.
Religion -- Study and teaching -- 19th century.; Education (Christian Theology); Annual reports.; Donations; Sermons.; Clergy -- United States.; Constitutions.; Membership lists.; Milnor, James, 1773-1845; Bates, Joshua, 1810-1888; Patton, William, 1798-1879; Frelinghuysen, Theodore, 1787-1862; Key, Frances Scott, 1779-1843; Mathews, J. M. (James McFarlane), 1785-1870; Spring, Gardiner, 1785-1873
- Sermon Delivered in Boston before The American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry by Reverend Eliphalet Pearson, Constitution, 1815 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "True Liberality" A Sermon, Preached in Boston on The First Anniversary of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry by Samuel Worcester, 1816 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Third Report of the Directors of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry, 1818 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Fourth Report of the Directors of the American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry, 1819 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Fifth Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1820 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Sixth Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1821 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Seventh Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1822 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Eighth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1823 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ninth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1824 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Tenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1826 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Eleventh Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1827 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Twelfth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1828 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Fourteenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1830 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Fifteenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1831 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sixteenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1832 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Seventeenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1833 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Eighteenth Annual Report of the Directors of the American Education Society, 1834 May (Box 1, Folder 17)